Hello English learners, welcome back to another show with us here at EnglishPod.
英语学习者你们好，欢迎回到 EnglishPod 的另一期节目。
My name is Marco.
我是 Marco。
And I'm Erika.
我是 Erika。
And today we're bringing you another romantic lesson but a little bit sad as well.
今天我们带来另一节浪漫课程，但也有点伤感。
That's right.
没错。
Today, unfortunately, our couple is going to be breaking up.
今天，不幸的是，我们的情侣要分手了。
Right, so it's a little bit sad today but it's going to be good because we're going
对，所以今天有点伤感，但会很好，因为我们要
to be teaching you some great words and phrases that you can use when you are faced in this
教你们一些很棒的单词和短语，当你们遇到这种
situation.
情况时可以用上。
Right, and so we're going to learn some phrases for breaking up and also some phrases for
对，所以我们要学习一些分手的短语，还有一些
staying together.
保持在一起的短语。
Alright, so let's listen to the dialogue for the first time and see what happens with our
好了，那我们第一次听对话，看看我们这对
young couple.
年轻情侣会发生什么。
Honey, do you have a second?
亲爱的，你有空吗？
Sure.
当然。
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You seem a bit worried.
你看起来有点担心。
What's on your mind?
你在想什么？
We need to talk.
我们需要谈谈。
Okay.
好的。
I've been thinking and well, I think we need to start seeing other people.
我一直在想，嗯，我觉得我们需要开始见别人了。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
I mean, we've had our ups and downs and we have the occasional disagreement but we're
我是说，我们有过起起落落，偶尔也有分歧，但我们
happy together, aren't we?
在一起很开心，不是吗？
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
我不再开心了，Tim。
It's not you, it's me.
不是你的问题，是我的问题。
I know that I can be hard to deal with and you're a great guy.
我知道我可能很难相处，你是个很棒的人。
You're the type of guy that any woman would kill for.
你是那种任何女人都会为之疯狂的男人。
So what are you saying?
所以你在说什么？
You're breaking up with me because I'm perfect?
你要跟我分手，因为我太完美了？
Tim, you are too good for me.
Tim，你对我太好了。
You deserve someone who can make you smile and make you happy the way that you made me
你值得一个能让你微笑、让你开心的人，就像你让我
happy.
开心那样。
I could say that I'll be all you need but that'd be a lie.
我可以说我会是你需要的一切，但那是谎言。
I know I'd only hurt you.
我知道我只会伤害你。
I know I'd only make you cry.
我知道我只会让你哭。
Baby, come on.
宝贝，别这样。
Don't do this to me.
别这样对我。
Whatever it is, we can work it out.
不管是什么，我们都能解决。
Just give me another chance.
再给我一次机会。
I know that we can get through this but we gotta stick together.
我知道我们能挺过去，但我们必须团结在一起。
Don't leave me.
别离开我。
I can't, Tim.
我不能，Tim。
I hope someday you can find some way to understand I'm only doing this for you.
我希望有一天你能理解，我这样做只是为了你。
I don't really want to go but deep in my heart, I know this is the kindest thing to do.
我真的不想走，但在我内心深处，我知道这是最仁慈的做法。
Laura.
Laura。
Here are your keys.
这是你的钥匙。
I'll send my sister to pick up the rest of my things next week.
我下周会让我妹妹来取我剩下的东西。
I'm sorry, Tim.
对不起，Tim。
I wish you all the best and I hope that one day we can meet again.
我祝你一切顺利，希望有一天我们能再见面。
I'll always love you.
我会永远爱你。
Goodbye.
再见。
Okay so a pretty sad ending to this relationship, isn't it?
好吧，这段关系结局挺伤感的，是吧？
Yeah, but I don't think the girl was very moved or very sad by breaking up with him.
是啊，但我觉得那个女孩分手时并没有很感动或很伤心。
I wonder why.
我想知道为什么。
Maybe she's got some other boyfriend somewhere else.
也许她在别处有别的男朋友。
Maybe.
也许吧。
Well, as you mentioned, we listened to some great phrases and it's time for us to take
嗯，正如你提到的，我们听到了一些很棒的短语，现在是时候在 Fluency Builder 中
a look at them now in Fluency Builder.
看看它们了。
Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder。
Okay, here we're going to focus on phrases that people use when they break up.
好的，这里我们要重点看人们分手时用的短语。
So maybe you've heard these in movies and we're going to look at the meaning now.
所以你可能在电影里听过这些，我们现在来看看它们的意思。
Alright, our first phrase, as we heard, she started by saying, we need to talk.
好了，我们的第一个短语，正如我们听到的，她开始说，我们需要谈谈。
We need to talk.
我们需要谈谈。
Alright, so it's a very direct sentence, we need to talk.
好的，这是一个非常直接的句子，我们需要谈谈。
So when you tell someone, we need to talk, you're telling them that you want to talk
所以当你告诉某人，我们需要谈谈，你是在告诉他们你想谈
about a serious thing, right?
一件严肃的事，对吧？
Right, so if somebody tells you, we need to talk, you know that you're going to talk about
对，所以如果有人告诉你，我们需要谈谈，你就知道你们要谈
a very serious matter.
一件非常严肃的事。
Yeah, a problem or a breakup or something.
是的，一个问题或分手之类的事。
And after that, she told him that they should start seeing other people.
之后，她告诉他他们应该开始见别人了。
Start seeing other people.
开始见别人。
Okay, I think we need to start seeing other people.
好的，我想我们需要开始见别人了。
To see other people.
见别人。
Alright, so this is very easy to understand.
好的，这很容易理解。
It means to?
它的意思是？
To date other people.
和别人约会。
Okay, so it basically means that you will break up.
好的，所以基本上意味着你们要分手了。
It's an indirect way of saying that, right?
这是一种间接的说法，对吧？
Yeah, you're not saying, hey, let's stop dating.
是的，你不是在说，嘿，我们别约会了。
You're saying, oh, well, maybe we should date other people and kind of giving the idea that
你在说，哦，嗯，也许我们应该和别人约会，暗示着
you will still date each other, but everyone knows you won't.
你们还会继续约会，但大家都知道不会。
Alright, so let's start seeing other people.
好了，那我们开始见别人吧。
Now for our third phrase.
现在看我们的第三个短语。
She says, it's not you, it's me.
她说，不是你的问题，是我的问题。
It's not you, it's me.
不是你的问题，是我的问题。
Now this is a very cliche phrase and you hear it all the time in movies and well, some people
这是一个非常老套的短语，你在电影里经常听到，嗯，有些人
still use it, right?
还在用，对吧？
Everyone says this.
每个人都这么说。
I've heard this.
我听过这个。
I've said this.
我说过这个。
Okay.
好的。
It means basically, I'm the problem.
它基本上意味着，我是问题所在。
You're not the problem.
你不是问题。
I'm the problem.
我是问题。
Right, so I am breaking up with you because it's my fault, not your fault.
对，所以我跟你分手是因为我的错，不是你的错。
Yeah, so it's kind of a nice way to break up with someone, but actually everyone knows
是的，所以这是一种比较温和的分手方式，但实际上大家都知道
that it's kind of a lie.
这有点假。
Not true, right?
不真实，对吧？
It is you.
是你。
You are the problem.
你才是问题。
Alright, so it's not you, it's me.
好了，所以不是你的问题，是我的问题。
And then, well, in order to emphasize this, that it's not his fault, she said that I know
然后，嗯，为了强调这不是他的错，她说我知道
I'm hard to deal with.
我很难相处。
So hard to deal with.
很难相处。
Okay, if somebody is hard to deal with.
好的，如果有人很难相处。
They're maybe difficult to talk to, difficult to please, maybe difficult to manage.
他们可能很难交谈，很难取悦，也许很难管理。
Okay, so it's very difficult to talk to that person.
好的，所以和那个人交谈非常困难。
Alright, hard to deal with.
好了，很难相处。
It's only for people.
这只用于人。
You can't use it for a situation or something else?
不能用于情况或其他东西吗？
No, you can use it for people or situations or even sometimes things.
不，你可以用于人、情况，甚至有时用于东西。
So for example, I can say, I find this problem at work so hard to deal with.
所以例如，我可以说，我觉得工作中的这个问题很难处理。
Okay, hard to deal with.
好的，很难处理。
So we've seen these four phrases that we can use to break up with someone.
所以我们看了这四个可以用来分手的短语。
And well, let's listen to our dialogue again.
嗯，让我们再听一遍我们的对话。
We're going to slow it down a little bit and then we'll come back and look at some other
我们会放慢一点速度，然后回来看看其他一些
phrases to stay together with someone.
用来和某人保持在一起的短语。
Honey, do you have a second?
亲爱的，你有空吗？
Sure.
当然。
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You seem a bit worried.
你看起来有点担心。
What's on your mind?
你在想什么？
We need to talk.
我们需要谈谈。
Okay.
好的。
I've been thinking and well, I think we need to start seeing other people.
我一直在想，嗯，我觉得我们需要开始见别人了。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
I mean, we've had our ups and downs and we have the occasional disagreement, but we're
我是说，我们有过起起落落，偶尔也有分歧，但我们
happy together, aren't we?
在一起很开心，不是吗？
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
我不再开心了，Tim。
It's not you.
不是你的问题。
It's me.
是我的问题。
I know that I can be hard to deal with and you're a great guy.
我知道我可能很难相处，你是个很棒的人。
You're the type of guy that any woman would kill for.
你是那种任何女人都会为之疯狂的男人。
So what are you saying?
所以你在说什么？
You're breaking up with me because I'm perfect?
你要跟我分手，因为我太完美了？
Tim, you are too good for me.
Tim，你对我太好了。
You deserve someone who can make you smile and make you happy the way that you made me
你值得一个能让你微笑、让你开心的人，就像你让我
happy.
开心那样。
I could say that I'll be all you need, but that'd be a lie.
我可以说我会是你需要的一切，但那是谎言。
I know I'd only hurt you.
我知道我只会伤害你。
I know I'd only make you cry.
我知道我只会让你哭。
Baby, come on.
宝贝，别这样。
Don't do this to me.
别这样对我。
Whatever it is, we can work it out.
不管是什么，我们都能解决。
Just give me another chance.
再给我一次机会。
I know that we can get through this, but we got to stick together.
我知道我们能挺过去，但我们必须团结在一起。
Don't leave me.
别离开我。
I can't, Tim.
我不能，Tim。
I hope someday you can find some way to understand I'm only doing this for you.
我希望有一天你能理解，我这样做只是为了你。
I don't really want to go, but deep in my heart, I know this is the kindest thing to
我真的不想走，但在我内心深处，我知道这是最仁慈的做法。
do.
做。
Laura.
Laura。
Here are your keys.
这是你的钥匙。
I'll send my sister to pick up the rest of my things next week.
我下周会让我妹妹来取我剩下的东西。
I'm sorry, Tim.
对不起，Tim。
I wish you all the best, and I hope that one day we can meet again.
我祝你一切顺利，希望有一天我们能再见面。
I'll always love you.
我会永远爱你。
Goodbye.
再见。
Okay, so as you said, we're now going to focus on the phrases you use to stay in a relationship
好的，正如你所说，我们现在要重点看用来维持关系的短语
with someone.
和某人在一起。
So let's look at those now in the Fluency Builder Part Two.
那我们现在在 Fluency Builder 第二部分看看这些。
Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder。
So the girl was trying to break up with him, and he kept on trying to convince her to stay.
所以女孩试图和他分手，他一直在试图说服她留下。
That's right.
没错。
And one of the things he said was, we've had our ups and downs.
他说的一件事是，我们有过起起落落。
We've had our ups and downs.
我们有过起起落落。
Ups and downs.
起起落落。
Well, ups and downs are good times and bad times.
嗯，起起落落就是好时光和坏时光。
Right.
对。
So the good times would be the ups and the bad times.
所以好时光就是起，坏时光就是
Obviously the downs.
落。
All right.
好的。
So it's an informal way of saying good times, bad times.
所以这是一种非正式的说法，表示好时光、坏时光。
So they've had their ups and downs, and he said we can work it out.
所以他们有过起起落落，他说我们可以解决。
We can work it out.
我们可以解决。
So whatever the problem is, we can work it out.
所以不管问题是什么，我们都能解决。
So why don't we hear some examples of how this phrase is used, and that will help us
那我们为什么不听听这个短语的一些例子呢，这会帮助我们
understand it a bit better.
更好地理解它。
Example one.
例子一。
Peter and Claudia were having some problems, but they finally worked out their personal
Peter 和 Claudia 有些问题，但他们最终解决了他们的个人
differences.
分歧。
Example two.
例子二。
We need to work out a new marketing plan for this upcoming quarter.
我们需要为即将到来的季度制定一个新的营销计划。
Example three.
例子三。
After an hour, I finally worked out the answer to this math problem.
一个小时后，我终于解出了这道数学题的答案。
Okay, so to work something out means to find a solution for it.
好的，所以解决某事意味着找到它的解决方案。
Yeah, to solve the problem.
是的，解决问题。
To solve the problem.
解决问题。
And again, he kept on insisting and saying, well, we can get through this.
他继续坚持说，嗯，我们能挺过去。
We can get through this.
我们能挺过去。
Okay, get through this.
好的，挺过去。
So to get through something.
所以挺过某事。
What does it mean to get through something?
挺过某事是什么意思？
Well, basically to survive a difficult situation.
嗯，基本上就是度过一个困难的情况。
Alright.
好的。
Or live through a difficult time.
或者挺过一段艰难时期。
Okay, so for them, the difficult time was this in their relationship.
好，对他们来说，这段艰难时期就是他们关系中的问题。
Yeah, or maybe you're having a problem at work, and you might say, hey guys, don't worry.
是啊，或者你在工作中遇到麻烦，你可能会说，嘿，各位，别担心。
We can get through this.
我们能挺过去的。
Just give us one more week.
再给我们一周时间。
Okay, very good.
好，非常好。
And well, as he was saying that they can get through this, he mentioned that they have
嗯，当他说他们能挺过去时，他提到他们必须
to stick together.
团结在一起。
To stick together.
We gotta stick together.
我们必须团结在一起。
Stick together.
团结在一起。
So again, to stick.
所以再次强调，粘在一起。
So when something sticks together, it stays together like glue.
所以当东西粘在一起时，就像胶水一样保持在一起。
Right, so they have to be a team and not separate in order to solve their problems.
对，所以他们必须成为一个团队，而不是分开，才能解决问题。
Exactly, it gives you that idea that they're gonna work together and stay together.
没错，这传达出他们会一起努力、保持团结的意思。
Okay, very good.
好，非常好。
So let's stick together.
那我们就团结在一起吧。
Alright so again, we have four great phrases to convince somebody or to say that you want
好的，再次强调，我们有四个很棒的短语来说服某人，或者说你想
to stay together in a relationship, right?
在一段关系中保持在一起，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
I think it'll help us to understand these if we hear them one more time in the dialogue.
我想如果我们再听一遍对话中的这些短语，会更容易理解。
Honey do you have a second?
亲爱的，你有空吗？
Sure.
当然。
Are you okay?
你还好吗？
You seem a bit worried.
你看起来有点担心。
What's on your mind?
你在想什么？
We need to talk.
我们需要谈谈。
Okay.
好的。
I've been thinking and well, I think we need to start seeing other people.
我一直在想，嗯，我觉得我们需要开始见见别人了。
What?
什么？
Why?
为什么？
I mean we've had our ups and downs and we have the occasional disagreement but we're
我是说我们有过起起落落，偶尔也有分歧，但我们
happy together, aren't we?
在一起很开心，不是吗？
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I'm not happy anymore, Tim.
我不再开心了，蒂姆。
It's not you, it's me.
不是你的问题，是我的问题。
I know that I can be hard to deal with and you're a great guy.
我知道我可能很难相处，而你是个很棒的人。
You're the type of guy that any woman would kill for.
你是那种任何女人都会为之疯狂的男人。
So what are you saying?
所以你在说什么？
You're breaking up with me because I'm perfect?
你要跟我分手，就因为我太完美了？
Tim, you are too good for me.
蒂姆，你对我太好了。
You deserve someone who can make you smile and make you happy the way that you made me
你值得一个能让你笑、让你开心的人，就像你曾经让我那样。
happy.
快乐。
I could say that I'll be all you need but that'd be a lie.
我可以说我会是你需要的一切，但那是谎话。
I know I'd only hurt you.
我知道我只会伤害你。
I know I'd only make you cry.
我知道我只会让你哭。
Baby, come on.
宝贝，快点。
Don't do this to me.
别这样对我。
Whatever it is we can work it out.
不管是什么问题，我们都能解决。
Just give me another chance.
再给我一次机会吧。
I know that we can get through this but we gotta stick together.
我知道我们能挺过去，但我们必须团结一致。
Don't leave me.
别丢下我。
I can't, Tim.
我做不到，蒂姆。
I hope someday you can find some way to understand I'm only doing this for you.
我希望有一天你能明白，我做这一切都是为了你。
I don't really want to go but deep in my heart I know this is the kindest thing to do.
我其实不太想去，但内心深处我知道这是最善良的做法。
Laura.
Laura。
Here are your keys.
这是你的钥匙。
I'll send my sister to pick up the rest of my things next week.
我下周会让我妹妹来取剩下的东西。
I'm sorry, Tim.
对不起，蒂姆。
I wish you all the best and I hope that one day we can meet again.
我祝你一切顺利，希望有一天我们能再见面。
I'll always love you.
我会永远爱你。
Goodbye.
再见。
I know I'd only hurt you.
我知道我只会伤害你。
I know I'd only make you cry.
我知道我只会让你哭。
I'm not the one you needed.
我不是你需要的那个人。
I love you.
我爱你。
Goodbye.
再见。
Alright, so breaking up can be a difficult situation, especially if you're the one breaking
好吧，分手确实是个棘手的情况，尤其是当你主动提分手的时候。
up, right?
起来，对吧？
Well, I guess it's never happy if you're the person who's being broken up with or you're
嗯，我想如果你是那个被甩的人，或者你是提出分手的人，都不会开心。
the person doing the breaking up.
提出分手的那个人。
But you know what?
但你知道吗？
I really noticed that a lot of the phrases the girl used to break up were very like cliche,
我确实注意到那个女孩用来分手的很多说法都非常老套。
like you said.
就像你说的。
They were very...
他们非常……
Common.
来吧。
Too common.
太普通了。
And kind of a joke almost.
几乎像个玩笑。
So the phrase, it's not you, it's me, it's one of them.
所以，“不是你的问题，是我的问题”这句话就是其中之一。
Yeah.
是啊。
And she also said you deserve better.
她还说你值得更好的。
You deserve someone better.
你值得一个更好的人。
Yeah.
是啊。
That's a very common one saying like, I'm not good enough for you.
这是很常见的一种说法，比如“我配不上你”。
Yeah.
是啊。
But again, it kind of just, it loses its meaning, doesn't it?
但同样，这种话有点失去意义了，不是吗？
And also another phrase that's very cliche, but it wasn't in our dialogue was maybe the
还有一个很老套的说法，虽然我们的对话里没有，就是
timing is just not right.
时机不对。
Yeah.
是啊。
People say that all the time.
人们总是这么说。
Yeah.
是啊。
So they say, no, the timing is not right.
所以他们就说，不，时机不对。
It's not the appropriate time to be together.
现在不是在一起的好时机。
Yeah.
是啊。
That's just an excuse for not wanting to date that special person.
那只是不想和那个特别的人约会的借口。
Exactly.
没错。
So it can be a difficult situation and people do it every day through letters, sometimes
所以这可能是个困难的情况，人们每天都这么做，有时通过信件，
through the phone.
有时通过电话。
Yeah.
是啊。
And sometimes it's just breaking up in person.
有时就直接当面分手。
So listeners, why don't you tell us if you have any stories of breaking up with someone
所以听众们，不如告诉我们，你们有没有和某人分手的经历，
or maybe somebody broke up with you.
或者有人和你分手的故事。
That's right.
没错。
Try and use the language in this lesson and visit us on our website at EnglishPod.com
试着用这节课里的语言，访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com，
and leave us a comment.
给我们留言。
All right.
好的。
We'll see you guys there and until next time.
我们到时候见，下次再见。
Thanks for listening and goodbye.
感谢收听，再见。
Goodbye.
再见。